Guide to the Peter V. Cacchione Papers TAM 073 (R-7823)
Tamiment Library / Wagner Archives
Peter V. Cacchione Papers
Bulk, 1944-1947
1936-1947, (Bulk 1944-1947)
TAM 073 (R-7823)
Tamiment Library / Wagner Archives
3.75 Linear feet (10 boxes)
Peter V. Cacchione was a labor leader, communist and New York City councilman. He took advantage of New York City's proportional representation system, and ran (unsuccessfully) for city council on the Communist Party ticket in 1937 and 1939. He was elected in 1941, 1943 and 1945 and served until his death in 1947. The collection includes his correspondence, speeches, wiritings, clippings, etc. from 1936-1947. Researchers must use microfilm (R-7823), except for series V, Scrapbooks.
Cacchione, Peter V., 1897-1947.
Box 1-10
Provenance
Gift of Dorothy Cacchione (widow), 1978.
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions. Patrons must use microfilm copy for materials in boxes 1-9 (R-7823), except for series V, Scrapbooks.
Historical/Biographical Note
Peter V. Cacchione (November 1, 1897 - November 6, 1947) was a labor leader, communist and New York City councilman. He was born of immigrant parents in Syracuse, New York in 1897, and grew up in Sayre, Pennsylvania. After graduating from high school in 1915 he worked as a railroad trainman and repairman, and at other blue-collar jobs. In 1932 he moved to New York, where he joined the progressive movement and in 1935 was elected National Commander of the Workers' Ex-Servicemen's League. In 1936 he became chairman of the Communist Party in the Bronx.
After moving to Brooklyn, he took advantage of New York City's newly instituted proportional representation system and ran (unsuccessfully) for city council on the Communist Party ticket in 1937 and 1939. He was elected in 1941, reelected in 1943 and 1945, and served until his death in 1947, two days after proportional representation was repealed. The New York City Council refused to seat the Communist Party's choice to serve the remaining fourteen months of Cacchione's term, his campaign manager (and biographer) Simon W. Gerson.
Sources:
Simon W. Gerson. Pete: the Story of Peter V. Cacchione, New York's First Communist Councilman, New York: International Publishers, 1976.
Scope and Content Note
The Correspondence series, arranged chronologically, includes John Cashmore, Luther Hill, Paul O'Dwyer, Michael J. Quill, Leo Rayfield, Nathan Sobel, Andrew Sommer, Henry Stimson, Harry S. Truman, Robert F. Wagner, Henry A. Wallace, and Walter Wilson.
The Speeches and Writings series contains It Happened at City Hall (Cacchione's Daily Worker column) and other articles, radio addresses, news releases, two unpublished Cacchione play typescripts, "Builders of America" and "Pageant for Columbus Day," and two book-length unpublished typescripts "What is Public Speaking?" and "A Few Simple Hints to Speakers," which are notable (especially the latter) for their use of 'how-to' examples based on numerous accounts of contemporary political issues, many at the grassroots level and ephemeral in nature.
The Topical Files series (arranged alphabetically) contains multiple files on discrimination, electoral campaigns (PVC, others), the five cent (bus and subway) fare, housing, proportional representation, resolutions (City Council and other) wartime price controls, and individual files on other local issues, and on Cacchione's 1947 national speaking tour.
The City Council series largely consists of PVC-issued Budget Questionnaire forms completed by officials of several hundred New York State cities, towns, and villages, and various documents and ephemera.
The last series consists of scrapbooks and loose material removed from scrapbooks (not microfilmed) documenting Cacchione's political career from 1939 to 1945.
Arrangement
Organized into five series: I. Correspondence; II. Speeches and Writings; III. Topical Files; IV. City Council; V. Scrapbooks (not microfilmed).
Folders are arranged alphabetically within each series.
Separated Material
There is no information about materials that are associated by provenance to the described materials that have been physically separated or removed.
Microfilm
Film R-7823
Cacchione, Peter V., 1897-1947.; Cashmore, John.; Communist Party of the United States of America (New York).; Hill, Luther.; O'Dwyer, Paul, 1907-; Quill, Mike.; Rayfield, Leo.; Sobel, Nathan R., 1906-; Sommer, Andrew.; Stimson, Henry L. (Henry Lewis), 1867-1950.; Truman, Harry S., 1884-1972.; Wagner, Robert F., (Robert Ferdinand), 1877-1953; Wallace, Henry A., (Henry Agard), 1888-1965; Wilson, Walter.; Addresses.; Articles.; Communists--United States.; Municipal government--New York (State)--New York.; New York (N.Y.); New York (N.Y.)--Politics and government--1898-1951.; Pamphlets.; Plays.; Press releases.; Proportional representation--New York (State)--New York.; Scrapbooks.; Typescripts.; Working class--United States.
- Series I: Correspondence
  - Correspondence, Outgoing, Sep 10, 1943-Jan 29, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    General note
    Reel 1
  - Correspondence, Outgoing, Feb 7, 1946-Jan 20, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, Outgoing, Jan 31, 1947-Mar 19, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, Outgoing, Mar 20, 1947-Oct 31, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, Incoming, May 1, 1943-Jan 5, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, Incoming, Jan 14, 1946-Oct 31, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, Incoming, Nov 11, 1946-May 6, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, Incoming, May 12, 1947-Nov 18, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, Third Party, Apr 1, 1943-May 15, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Series II: Speeches & Writings
  - Radio Addresses, Oct 20, 1937-Aug 1, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 1`)
  - News Releases, Dec 12, 1944-Apr 3, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - News Releases, May 17, 1946-Jun 25, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Articles, Jan 8, 1945-1946 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Articles, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Public Speaking: A Guide Book (by PVC). Workers Library Publishers, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - "What is Public Speaking?" (typescript, approx 170 p.), undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - "A Few Simple Hints to Speakers" (typescript, 94 p.), 1938 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - "It Happened at City Hall" (PVC Daily Worker column), Jan 2, 1944-Mar 12, 1944 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - "It Happened at City Hall", Mar 19, 1944-May 21, 1944 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - "It Happened at City Hall", May 28, 1944-Aug 13, 1944 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - It Happened at City Hall", Aug 20, 1944-Oct 29, 1944 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - "It Happened at City Hall", Nov 5, 1944-Jan 21, 1945 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - "It Happened at City Hall", Feb 4, 1945-Apr 1, 1945 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - "It Happened at City Hall", Apr 8, 1945-Jan 27, 1946 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - "It Happened at City Hall", Feb 3, 1946-Jun 23, 1946 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - "It Happened at City Hall", Jun 30, 1946-Sep 27, 1946 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - "It Happened at City Hall", Oct 7, 1946-Jan 4, 1947 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - PVC Plays: Builders of America, Pageant for Columbus Day, undated (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Series III: Topical Files
  - Antonini, Luigi, Apr 6, 1943-May, 1943 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    Reel 2
  - Ballots & Nominating Petitions, 1945 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Baseball, Jun 7, 1943-May 22, 1947 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Bilbo - Piccolo, 1945 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Brooklyn History - Sketches, undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Budget (PVC re NYC budget), May 24, 1944-Oct 17, 1946 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    Film R-7823, Reel 2
  - Child Care, Dec 26, 1944-Sep 9, 1947 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - City Departments, Jan 5, 1945-May 9, 1947 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Discrimination, General, Mar 25, 1942-Feb 24, 1944 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Discrimination, General, Feb 25, 1944-Feb 6, 1945 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Discrimination, General, Mar 19, 1945-Sep 7, 1946 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Discrimination, General, undated (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Discrimination, Black, Jan, 1940 -May 9, 1946 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Discrimination, Black, Feb 17, 1947-Oct 8, 1947 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Discrimination, Education, May 25, 1940-May 9, 1946 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Discrimination, Education, May 13, 1946-Mar 13, 1947 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Discrimination, Education, undated (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Discrimination, Textbooks, Mar 21, 1946-Jun 30, 1947 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Displaced Persons, Nov 25, 1946-Dec 31, 1946 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Dog Vaccine, Jan 21, 1947-Feb 4, 1947 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Drew Case, Jan 27, 1943-Feb 20, 1944 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Education, General, Apr 1944 -Jul 5, 1946 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Education, General, Jul 12, 1946-Sep 29, 1947 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Election, General, Oct 17, 1937-Nov 20, 1942 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Election, General, Sep 14, 1943-Oct 31, 1947 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Election Pamphlets - English Language, undated (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Election Pamphlets - English Language, undated (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Election Pamphlets - English Language, undated (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Election Pamphlets - Black, undated (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Election Pamphlets - Hispanic, Polish, Hebrew, Italian, undated (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Election Pamphlets - Non-Cacchione, undated (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Election, Statistics, 1937-1943 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Election, Statistics, 1944-1946 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Electric Company, 1936-22-Sep-42 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Electric Company, Nov 6, 1942-1946 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Five Cent Fare, 1937-Mar 14, 1944 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    Reel 3
  - Five Cent Fare, Mar 15, 1944-Mar 21, 1944 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Five Cent Fare, Mar 23, 1944-Apr 11, 1944 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Five Cent Fare, Apr 12, 1944-Feb 18, 1945 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Five Cent Fare, Feb 19, 1945-Mar 2, 1945 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Five Cent Fare, Mar 4, 1945-Mar 16, 1945 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Five Cent Fare, Mar 16, 1945-Mar 22, 1945 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Five Cent Fare, Mar 22, 1945-Aug 16, 1945 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Five Cent Fare, Oct 29, 1946-Mar 7, 1947 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Five Cent Fare, undated (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Five Cent Fare, undated (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Five Cent Fare - PVC Statement to Board of Estimate, Feb 11, 1947 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Flatbush Water, Jan 3, 1946-Jul 1, 1947 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Foreign Born, May 28, 1946-May, 1947 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Gas Companies, Apr 28, 1947-May 12, 1947 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Housing, Mar 23, 1944-Dec 19, 1945 (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Housing, Jan 9, 1946-May 2, 1946 (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Housing, May 11, 1946-Aug 10, 1946 (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Housing, Oct 25, 1946-Mar 2, 1947 (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - Housing, Mar 13, 1947-Jun 10, 1947 (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - Housing, Jun 12, 1947-Jul 18, 1947 (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - Housing, Jul 23, 1947-Oct 16, 1947 (Box 6, Folder 22)
  - Housing, undated (Box 6, Folder 23)
  - Invitations, Oct 19, 1941-Nov 9, 1947 (Box 6, Folder 24)
  - Italy & Italian Americans, Mar 3, 1939-Oct 12, 1947 (Box 6, Folder 25)
  - Jews & Palestine, Sep 22, 1938-May 26, 1947 (Box 6, Folder 26)
  - Libraries, Feb, 1945-Jul 8, 1947 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Literacy Tests, 1937-1944 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Long Island Railroad, Jan 13, 1947-Apr 4, 1947 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Milk, Feb 14, 1943-Oct 22, 1947 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - National Tour, Jul 24, 1947-Sep 30, 1947 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Police, Sep 16, 1946-Sep 26, 1947 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Poll Tax, Jan 6, 1943-Feb 9, 1945 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Prices, Food, Office of Price Administration, Dec 22, 1942-Aug 23, 1944 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Prices, Food, Office of Price Administration, Sep 26, 1944-May 11, 1945 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Prices, Food, Office of Price Administration, May 14, 1945-Jun 7, 1945 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Prices, Food, Office of Price Administration, Jun 8, 1945-Jul 14, 1947 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Prices, Food, Office of Price Administration, Jul 22, 1947-Aug 12, 1947 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Proportional Representation - National Municipal Survey, 1947 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Proportional Representation - National Municipal Survey, 1947 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Proportional Representation...Survey, 1947 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Proportional Representation...Survey, 1947 (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Proportional Representation...Survey, 1947 (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Proportional Representation, Jul 7, 1947-Oct 31, 1947 (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - Proportional Representation, undated (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - Proportional Representation - Pamphlets, 1947 (Box 7, Folder 20)
  - Proportional Representation - Guides, 1937-1947 (Box 7, Folder 21)
  - Religion, 1946-1947 (Box 7, Folder 22)
  - Resolutions, City Council, 1942-1943 (Box 7, Folder 23)
  - Resolutions, City Council, 1944 (Box 7, Folder 24)
  - Resolutions, City Council, 1945 (Box 7, Folder 25)
  - Resolutions, City Council, 1946 (Box 7, Folder 26)
  - Resolutions, City Council, 1947 (Box 7, Folder 27)
  - Resolutions, City Council - Misc. & Taken Over Bills, 1944-1947 (Box 7, Folder 28)
  - Resolutions, City Council - Letters, May 16, 1944-Aug 24, 1944 (Box 7, Folder 29)
  - Resolutions, Letters, Jan 29, 1946-Jul 22, 1946 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    Reel 4
  - Resolutions, Letters, Jul 24, 1946-Jan 14, 1947 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Resolutions, Letters, Jan 21, 1947-Mar 10, 1947 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Resolutions, Letters, Mar 10, 1947-Mar 19, 1947 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Resolutions, Letters, Mar 19, 1947-Mar 24, 1947 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Resolutions, Letters, Mar 26, 1947-Apr 15, 1947 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Resolutions, Letters, May 22, 1947-Oct 29, 1947 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Sales Tax, Mar 16, 1943-Apr 4, 1946 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Sales Tax, Apr 5, 1946-Dec 3, 1946 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Seamen, Nov 27, 1944-May 8, 1946 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Schwellenbach Proposal to Outlaw CPUSA; Clemente Bill, 1947 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Social Services, Jun 27, 1945-Mar 6, 1946 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Spellman, Cardinal, Mar 5, 1946-May 19, 1946 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Statistical Reports, 1940-1947 (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Statistics (Electoral) on the Communist Party, undated (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - Subscriptions (PVC to various periodicals), 1947 (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - Succession, 1947 (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - Teacher Salaries, Nov 27, 1945-Feb 10, 1947 (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - Tenants' Organizations, Feb 6, 1946-Oct 28, 1947 (Box 8, Folder 19)
  - Transit & Transportation Problems, 1944-1946 (Box 8, Folder 20)
  - Walter Wilson Public Relations, Jan 7, 1946-Feb 27, 1946 (Box 8, Folder 21)
  - Veterans Affairs, Mar 20, 1944-Feb 10, 1947 (Box 8, Folder 22)
  - Veterans Affairs, Feb 26, 1947-Sep, 1947 (Box 8, Folder 23)
  - YMCA Strike, Mar 15, 1947-Jun 7, 1947 (Box 8, Folder 24)
  - Yugoslavia, 1946 (Box 8, Folder 25)
- Series IV: City Council
  - City Council, 1942-1943 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - City Council, 1944-1946 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Budget Questionnaire (New York State: Towns, Villages & Cities), 1947 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Budget Questionnaire, 1947 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Budget Questionnaire, 1947 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Budget Questionnaire, 1947 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Budget Questionnaire, 1947 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Budget Questionnaire, 1947 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Budget Questionnaire, 1947 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Budget Questionnaire, 1947 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Budget Questionnaire, 1947 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Budget Questionnaire, 1947 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Budget Questionnaire, 1947 (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Budget Questionnaire, 1947 (Box 9, Folder 14)
- Series V: Scrapbooks (not microfilmed).
  - Scrapbook (I), 1939 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Scrapbook (II), 1939 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Scrapbook (I), 1941 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Scrapbook (II), 1941 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Oversize Scrapbook (loose items): Clippings, 1939-1945 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Oversize Scrapbook (loose items): Correspondence, 1939-1945 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Oversize Scrapbook (loose items): Event Invitations and Programs, 1939-1945 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Oversize Scrapbook (loose items): Flyers, 1939-1945 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Oversize Scrapbook (loose items): Holiday Cards and Other Ephemera, 1939-1945 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Oversize Scrapbook (loose items): Press Releases, 1939-1945 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Oversize Scrapbook (loose items): Typescripts, 1939-1945 (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Oversize Scrapbook (includes clippings, flyers, press releases, and a small number of photographs relating to Cacchione's political career), 1939-1945 (Box 11, Folder 1)